William Jarvie Society records
Columbia University Medical Center
William Jarvie Society records
1947 - 2005
Meeting minutes, correspondence (1947-1974) and one newsletter (2005) created by the William Jarvie Society, a student organization in the School of Dental and Oral Surgery--later known as the College of Dental Medicine.
0.33 cubic feet (1 box)
William Jarvie Society
Augustus C. Long Health Sciences Library 701 W. 168th Street HHSC LL1-111 New York, NY 10032 Archives & Special Collections
Images of members and information regarding the William Jarvie Society may be found in the yearbook, Dental Columbian.
Archives & Special Collections also holds the personal papers of William Jarvie.
Irregular accruals.
The date and circumstances of accession are unknown. The Society holds copyright for their materials.
Open for research.
Founded in 1920 by William Gies and named for Jarvie, a Brooklyn dentist known for promoting dental education and research. Self-described as the student honor and research society of the Columbia University School of Dental and Oral Surgery, the organization was founded with the goal of promoting research among students in order to advance dentistry and to provide opportunities for students to participate in research at Columbia University. The organization also serves as the Columbia chapter of the American Association of Dental Research (AADR).
The Society published a short-lived quarterly, Stomatology references current medical literature (1963-1965?), and the Journal of the William Jarvie Society, beginning in 1969 which continues to the present day under the title Jarvie.
The renamed William Jarvie Research Society continues to be active with students at Columbia University’s College of Dental Medicine.
References
Columbia University School of Dental and Oral Surgery, Dental Columbian ([New York, N.Y.]: The students,1969), 78.
Jarvie: Journal of the William Jarvie Society (New York, N.Y.: William Jarvie Society, College of Dental Medicine, Columbia University, 2001), 5.
Columbia University. School of Dental and Oral Surgery; Dental students--New York (State)--New York; Dentistry--Research; Schools, Dental; Columbia University. College of Dental Medicine; Minutes (Records)
Meeting minutes and correspondence arranged annually. The bulk of the correspondence consists of letters graciously accepting membership into the Society. Contains class rank information since membership candidates came from the top half of their classes. Meeting topics also include proposed lectures, social affairs, changes to their bylaws and constitutions, and special projects. Includes one newsletter from 2005.
Arranged annually.
- Minutes and correspondence, 1947/48-1950/51 (Box-folder 1.1)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1951/52-1953/54 (Box-folder 1.2)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1954/55-1955/56 (Box-folder 1.3)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1956/57-1957/58 (Box-folder 1.4)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1958/59 (Box-folder 1.5)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1959/60 (Box-folder 1.6)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1960/61 (Box-folder 1.7)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1961/62-1964/65 (Box-folder 1.8)
- Minutes and correspondence, 1970/71-1973/74 (Box-folder 1.9)
- Newsletter, v. 7, no. 1 (Spring: 2005) (Box-folder 1.10)